<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from Ierusalem containing, 1. The beauty of the citie of the great King. 2. The vanitie of the isles of the sonns of men. 3. The comming of the Kings sonne. VVritten by Augustin Taylor, preacher at Hawarden.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Augustine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846711</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11698</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13413)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11698)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1036:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from Ierusalem containing, 1. The beauty of the citie of the great King. 2. The vanitie of the isles of the sonns of men. 3. The comming of the Kings sonne. VVritten by Augustin Taylor, preacher at Hawarden.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Augustine.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Matthewes, dwelling in the parsonage house in Bride Lane, neere Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>"The miserie of the world" (prose) and "The comming of the Kings sonne" each have separate dated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11698:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11698:1"/>
            <p>NEWES FROM IERVSALEM:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Containing,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The beauty of the Citie of the great King.</item>
                  <item>2. The Vanitie of the Iſles of the ſonns of men.</item>
                  <item>3. The comming of the Kings Sonne.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>Tom pulchra es Amica mea, non eſt macula in te. <bibl>
                  <hi>Cant. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Written by AVGVSTIN TAYLOR, <hi>Preacher at</hi> Hawarden.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Augustine Matthewes,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Parſonage houſe in Bride Lane, neere Fleet-ſtreet. 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable ANNE, the Lady CARRE, onely Daughter to the thrice Noble Lord, WILLIAM Earle of DARBY, &amp;c.</head>
                  <l>IF it may pleaſe you to Suruey,</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Lines</hi> with th'eyes of Grace,</l>
                  <l>You'll not repent, for ſurely they</l>
                  <l>Doe Ayme at <hi>Glories</hi> Place.</l>
                  <l>They are your Owne; I did intend</l>
                  <l>When I was great with yong</l>
                  <l>Of theſe Conceptions, ſome great Friend</l>
                  <l>Should Patronage my Song.</l>
                  <l>And may with Honour, Sacred things</l>
                  <l>Can nere be lodg'd too well;</l>
                  <l>Gods holy Truth in breſts of Kings</l>
                  <l>Beſeemeth beſt to dwell.</l>
                  <l>Most Vertuous Noble <hi>Lady,</hi> I</l>
                  <l>Haue (from your Bounty) wing,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:3"/>
                  <l>And whilſt my Muſe hath power to fly,</l>
                  <l>Some holy Offering</l>
                  <l>She will preferre, The Body may</l>
                  <l>Wi h all her parts agree</l>
                  <l>To rule the minde; but I dare ſay,</l>
                  <l>The Soule can neuer bee</l>
                  <l>Contain'd in ſuch baſe limits. No!</l>
                  <l>It aymes at better things,</l>
                  <l>And cannot reſt vntill it know,</l>
                  <l>That Campe where's none but Kings.</l>
                  <l>Great and Good Lady, hold your Hand,</l>
                  <l>And to requite your paynes,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall more true Ioy vnderſtand,</l>
                  <l>Then all the world containes.</l>
                  <l>Peruſe this well, and if it doth</l>
                  <l>Your inward Thoughts aduance,</l>
                  <l>Giue God the Praiſe and Honour both,</l>
                  <l>And mee your Countenance.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Euer diſpoſed to bee at your Honourable diſpoſe,</hi> Auguſtine Taylor.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:3"/>
                  <head>THE GREAT KINGS CITIE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="1">1 A Ariſe my ſoule from death and Hell,</l>
                     <l>Soare with the wings of Loue,</l>
                     <l>To ſee where Saints and Angels dwell</l>
                     <l>with God in bliſſe aboue.</l>
                     <l n="2">2 Remember thou a ſtranger art,</l>
                     <l>and wand'ring Pilgrim here,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall be vntill thou depart</l>
                     <l>to Saints thy fellowes there.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="3">3 An exile poore on earth oppreſt</l>
                     <l>amongſt profeſſed Foes,</l>
                     <l>The World, the Fleſh, the Diuels proteſt</l>
                     <l>to multiply thy woes:</l>
                     <l n="4">4 Immortall Soule why is't thou ſtayes</l>
                     <l>to build thy Houſe on Sand,</l>
                     <l>The Bridegroome comes, the muſicke plaies,</l>
                     <l>the Marriage is at hand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:4"/>
                     <l n="5">5 A wedding garment thou muſt haue,</l>
                     <l>I meane a vertuous life:</l>
                     <l>For other garments are not graue</l>
                     <l>for ſuch a Princ s wife.</l>
                     <l n="6">6 Therefore renounce all earthly pelfe,</l>
                     <l>a heauenly Race to runne,</l>
                     <l>Forſake the world, and frame thy ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>To liue as Saints haue done.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="7">7 Aſcend aboue the Azure skie,</l>
                     <l>and things that mortall be,</l>
                     <l>Beyond the ſtarry Heauens hie,</l>
                     <l>if thou true ioyes would ſee.</l>
                     <l n="8">8 A Citie there prepared is,</l>
                     <l>for ſtately Order rare,</l>
                     <l>A Princely place adorn'd with bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſumptuous buildings faire,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="9">9 <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that place is call'd,</l>
                     <l>moſt glorious to behold,</l>
                     <l>The which with precious ſtones is wall'd,</l>
                     <l>whoſe ſtreets are pau'd with gold.</l>
                     <l n="10">10 Amid the ſtreets the well of Life,</l>
                     <l>with golden Streames doth flow,</l>
                     <l>Vpon whoſe Bankes the Tree of Life</l>
                     <l>in ſeemely ſort doth grow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:4"/>
                     <l n="11">11 With pleaſant fruits of euery kind,</l>
                     <l>fit for immortall taſte,</l>
                     <l>Vpon whoſe root there ſhalt thou ſind,</l>
                     <l>the heauenly Manna plac'd.</l>
                     <l n="12">12 There <hi>Dauid</hi> ſits with Harpe in hand,</l>
                     <l>as Maſter of the Quire,</l>
                     <l>Moſt happy thoſe that vnderſtand,</l>
                     <l>and may his Muſicke heare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="13">13 There <hi>Noah</hi> with all the Iuſt doth raigne,</l>
                     <l>There doe the Prophets land,</l>
                     <l>Patriarkes old doe there remaine</l>
                     <l>with ſcepters in their hands.</l>
                     <l n="14">14 There all our good progenitors,</l>
                     <l>doe wiſh and wayt for thee,</l>
                     <l>And thouſands of thine Anceſtors,</l>
                     <l>which thou didſt neuer ſee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="15">15 There millions of bright Angels be,</l>
                     <l>and Saints in glory braue,</l>
                     <l>And euery one is glad to ſee</l>
                     <l>the ioyes their fellowes haue.</l>
                     <l n="16">16 There Marryrs and Apoſtles liue,</l>
                     <l>there ſacred Virgins ſtay,</l>
                     <l>There they doe wayt, and duely giue</l>
                     <l>attendance night and day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:5"/>
                     <l n="17">17 There bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> ſweetly ſings,</l>
                     <l>with ſweet melodious voyce,</l>
                     <l>The Saints, and all Caeleſtiall things,</l>
                     <l>for Ioy with her reioyce.</l>
                     <l n="18">18 Sad <hi>Magdalen</hi> hath left her moane,</l>
                     <l>her ſighes, and ſobbs doe ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>Now all her teares and griefes are gone,</l>
                     <l>and ſhee's in endleſſe peace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="19">19 Ten thouſand tongues cannot expound,</l>
                     <l>nor Angels skill indite,</l>
                     <l>The paſsing pleaſures there abound,</l>
                     <l>the Ioyes that there delight.</l>
                     <l n="20">20 There is combin'd the complete ſumme,</l>
                     <l>that loued to liue well:</l>
                     <l>There all the Kings in order come,</l>
                     <l>that honou'd <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="21">21 There ſhalt thou ſee the Cherubins,</l>
                     <l>in glorious State excell,</l>
                     <l>The Angels and the Seraphins,</l>
                     <l>where ſoules of Saints doe dwell.</l>
                     <l n="22">22 O happy time to meet our Friends,</l>
                     <l>and louing Kinsfolke there,</l>
                     <l>To line in bliſſe that neuer ends,</l>
                     <l>with them we lou'd ſo deare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:5"/>
                     <l n="23">23 No bliſſe nor pleaſure there doth want,</l>
                     <l>that man may wiſh to haue:</l>
                     <l>No Ioyes, nor true delights are ſcant,</l>
                     <l>thou canſt deuiſe to craue.</l>
                     <l n="24">24 If Wealth or Honour thou deſire,</l>
                     <l>or Happy dayes to ſee,</l>
                     <l>There nothing wants thou canſt require,</l>
                     <l>for thou a Prince ſhalt bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="25">25 Thy Garments ſhall be all of bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>thou ſhalt a Scepter beare,</l>
                     <l>And Dyadem more precious is,</l>
                     <l>then earthly Princes weare.</l>
                     <l n="26">26 If thou deſireſt daintie Cheere,</l>
                     <l>and rich and coſtly Meat;</l>
                     <l>The Bread and Drinke of Life is there,</l>
                     <l>and food that Angels eat.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="27">27 In aged yeares, if thou requeſt</l>
                     <l>to liue with faithfull friends,</l>
                     <l>With Saints and Angels thou ſhalt reſt,</l>
                     <l>in bliſſe that neuer ends.</l>
                     <l n="28">28 If Learning, Wiſdome, Wit, or Health,</l>
                     <l>may ſatisfie thy mind,</l>
                     <l>A boundleſſe, endleſſe Common-wealth,</l>
                     <l>is there for thee aſsign'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:6"/>
                     <l n="29">29 Or if thou liſt in reuerend wiſe,</l>
                     <l>the will of God to doe,</l>
                     <l>There is the Church, the Sacrifice,</l>
                     <l>the Prieſt, and Altar too.</l>
                     <l n="30">30 There God himſelf doth heare our plaints,</l>
                     <l>and pities Chriſtians caſe,</l>
                     <l>Our ancient friends (now holy Saints)</l>
                     <l>beholds him face to face.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="31">31 There triumph ouer ſinne is wonne,</l>
                     <l>the Deuil, and Death defac'd,</l>
                     <l>The Kingdome of the Iuſt begunne,</l>
                     <l>and there in glory plac'd:</l>
                     <l n="32">32 There Tyrants nothing haue to doe,</l>
                     <l>nor Racke, nor Rope is knowne:</l>
                     <l>Tormentors all, and Sathan too,</l>
                     <l>are fully ouerthrowne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="33">33 To liue vpon this Earth a King,</l>
                     <l>ten thouſand yeares, I ſay:</l>
                     <l>To thee ſuch pleaſure cannot bring,</l>
                     <l>as there to liue a day.</l>
                     <l n="34">34 No rude nor rayling Heretique,</l>
                     <l>that ſtrange Religion make:</l>
                     <l>No temporizing Schiſmatique,</l>
                     <l>that Chriſt and Church forſake,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:6"/>
                     <l n="35">35 Shall enter there, or finde a place,</l>
                     <l>wherein to take repoſe:</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that haue liu'd the life of grace,</l>
                     <l>the life of glory knowes</l>
                     <l n="36">36 Nothing vncleane nothing impure,</l>
                     <l>can bee admitted there.</l>
                     <l>God loues what's like himſelfe be ſure,</l>
                     <l>things ſpotleſſe, bright, and cleare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="37">37 For Enuy there's no place to reſt,</l>
                     <l>foule Blaſphemy's debarr'd,</l>
                     <l>Slaunder preſumes to be a Gheſt,</l>
                     <l>but Heauen was prepar'd</l>
                     <l n="38">38 For no ſuch ſtuffe; Ambition may</l>
                     <l>ſuppoſe t'aſcend on hye:</l>
                     <l>But that's an errour, there's no ſtay</l>
                     <l>for ſuch Societie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="39">39 Ioy, Pietie, Bountie, Patience, Faith,</l>
                     <l>are ſure to ſoare aboue:</l>
                     <l>For Sion (as the Ancients ſaith)</l>
                     <l>was built for Peace and Loue.</l>
                     <l n="40">40 This place is free from Need and Night,</l>
                     <l>for Day and plentie laſts:</l>
                     <l>Chriſts is the Sunne of endleſſe light,</l>
                     <l>not ſubiect t'ouer-caſts.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:7"/>
                     <l n="41">41 The bodies there of euery one,</l>
                     <l>exceeds the Chryſtall cleare,</l>
                     <l>And ſhines farre brighter then the Sunne,</l>
                     <l>when it doth fair'ſt appeare:</l>
                     <l n="42">42 No Moone, nor Starres, nor Candles there</l>
                     <l>can profit any whit:</l>
                     <l>They ſhew much like as clouds doe heare,</l>
                     <l>that yeeld no benefit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="43">43 The Citizens thereof are Saints,</l>
                     <l>the Gouernour's the Lambe;</l>
                     <l>No Treaſure, neither pleaſure wants,</l>
                     <l>that God can giue to man.</l>
                     <l n="44">44 And if <hi>Iehouah</hi> vſe his skill,</l>
                     <l>to make a place compleat,</l>
                     <l>To praiſe the worke of his beſt will,</l>
                     <l>none can but thoſe that ſee't.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="45">45 Who cannot comprehend, admire,</l>
                     <l>and we ſhall ſee in time,</l>
                     <l>The ſtate of thoſe that doe aſpire</l>
                     <l>to that celeſtiall Clyme.</l>
                     <l n="46">46 Remooue your thoughts to better things,</l>
                     <l>the nature of the mind,</l>
                     <l>Aſpires, and ſeekes a campe of Kings,</l>
                     <l>and cannot be confin'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:7"/>
                     <l n="47">47 A King a time may be contain'd</l>
                     <l>vnder the pooreſt roofe:</l>
                     <l>But long no Monarch ſo remain'd,</l>
                     <l>I need to bring no proofe.</l>
                     <l n="48">48 Euen ſo the ſoule awhile may night</l>
                     <l>within weake walls of clay,</l>
                     <l>But wayts the time to take her flight,</l>
                     <l>to finde a better day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="49">49 Then ſince there is no certaine good</l>
                     <l>allotted heere below:</l>
                     <l>Get wings againſt another Flood,</l>
                     <l>and teach thy ſelfe to know,</l>
                     <l n="50">50 The Towers of <hi>Bethell, Babells</hi> downe,</l>
                     <l>and like to riſe no more,</l>
                     <l>Except to fall; ſeeke thou the Towne,</l>
                     <l>from which old <hi>Simon</hi> bore</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="51">51 His Maſters Croſſe; for thou muſt paſſe</l>
                     <l>the Valley to the Mount,</l>
                     <l>Then change thy ſelfe from what thou was,</l>
                     <l>and make a full account,</l>
                     <l n="52">52 To leaue the earthly Citie, and</l>
                     <l>prepare thy ſelfe to ſing,</l>
                     <l>Such Songs as fits the Holy Land,</l>
                     <l>to praiſe ſo great a King.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:8"/>
                     <l n="53">53 O let no graceleſſe Syrens Song,</l>
                     <l>thy graces ouer-caſt:</l>
                     <l>If thou want ſtrength to come along,</l>
                     <l>binde thy ſelfe to the Maſt</l>
                     <l n="54">54 Of Heauens holy Ship, the Church;</l>
                     <l>yet there thou mayſt be toſt:</l>
                     <l>But for her ſafeſt Harbour ſearch,</l>
                     <l>and thou canſt not be loſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="55">55 The Owner of the Ship may winke,</l>
                     <l>and Paſſengers may weepe,</l>
                     <l>When they as <hi>Peter</hi> thought, doe thinke</l>
                     <l>the Maſter is aſleepe,</l>
                     <l n="56">56 And Windes and Seas doe threaten death,</l>
                     <l>but then like <hi>Peter</hi> call;</l>
                     <l>And Windes, and Seas, and Hell beneath,</l>
                     <l>confeſſe t'obey him all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="57">57 Who may it bee that theſe obey?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iehouahs</hi> onely Sonne,</l>
                     <l>Sayling for Heauen: Happy they</l>
                     <l>that in this paſſage runne</l>
                     <l n="58">58 Each one will venture to find Land,</l>
                     <l>that yeelds ſmall Gemmes of price,</l>
                     <l>And for a trifle take in hand</l>
                     <l>a tedious enterpriſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:8"/>
                     <l n="59">59 As 'twas, it is, Canaans Gold,</l>
                     <l>is graceleſſely refuſ'd,</l>
                     <l>For Straw in Egypt: but why ſhould</l>
                     <l>the beſt be thus abuſ'd?</l>
                     <l n="60">60 Why buy men prophane Bookes apace,</l>
                     <l>and leaue the ſacred Story?</l>
                     <l>For want of grace; and want of grace</l>
                     <l>will breed the want of glory.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="61">61 Therefore you that deſire thoſe things,</l>
                     <l>prepar'd with God aboue,</l>
                     <l>Contemne the world, and take the wings</l>
                     <l>of Faith of Hope, and Loue.</l>
                     <l n="62">62 The Heauens are ope, the Way is light,</l>
                     <l>true Ioyes abounds amaine:</l>
                     <l>The Lambe and Bride in glory bright,</l>
                     <l>eternally ſhall raigne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="63">63 In Perſons three, in Eſſence one,</l>
                     <l>God grant we all adore;</l>
                     <l>Not onely euermore alone,</l>
                     <l>but euer, more and more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:9"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:9"/>
                  <p>THE MISERIE OF THE WORLD.</p>
                  <p>Or <hi>The Vanitie of the Iſles of</hi> the ſonnes of men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoc momentum vnde pendet aeternitas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By AVGVSTIN TAYLOR, <hi>Preacher at</hi> Hawarden.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Augustine Matthewes,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Parſonage houſe. in Bride Lane, neere Fleet-ſtreet. 1623.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:10"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:10"/>
                  <head>To the Right Worſhipfull WILLIAM RAVENSCROFT, <hi>Eſquire, &amp;c. a Principall of the</hi> Honourable Societie of Lincolnes Inne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir, it hath been a proper cuſtome in all ages amongſt all (but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the beſt) ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to requite euery benefit (at the leaſt with gratitude,) for it is found in the rules of humane equity, <hi>non datur be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficium, niſi propter oſſicium,</hi> and if it be ſo, that no benefit is beſtowed, but in regard of ſome office to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for it, then your bounties weekely beſtowed in ſo large meaſure in our Church of <hi>Hawarden,</hi> towards the reliefe of them moſt needfull in that Juriſdiction) deſerues a publike teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall of many thankefull voices, and not to be a requitall to you, but to be an excitall to others to doe the like. In a word, your datiue acte vnto your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue place ſhall finde rewards at God, and ſhould finde imitation, but ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:11698:11"/>finde commendation with men: being an acte both good, great, and laſting. And ſince your bounties (truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued) are Gods bleſsings, J take it to belong to mee to erect ſome columne in your memoriall, in the behalfe of thoſe that in ſo great meaſure taſte your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious gifts, for ſince I am appointed to offer their ſacrifice to God, I am like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe allotted to conduct their thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to you; not to flatter you, for I know you are not vaine glorious, becauſe it is knowen you are charitable: &amp; charitie and vaine-glory were neuer yet cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berfellowes; and therefore that (as you doe) you may ſtill ſeeke for thoſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures aboue, I preſent you with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of theſe trifles below; the baſenes of the latter, inuites you to purſue the excellencie of the former: and as you haue begun with Grace, ſo without queſtion you ſhall finiſh with glory, which is the earneſt deſire of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your worſhips in the ſeruice of God, AVGVSTIN TAYLOR.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:11"/>
                  <head>THE MISERIE OF THF WORLD.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any one long after life, and deſires to ſee good dayes, let him refraine his tongue from euill, remooue his feete out of the paths of Impietie, hold his hands from all actes of Seuerity, waſh his heart from all thoughts of impuritie, and then willingly caſt aſide the coate of Iniquity; and hauing put it off, put it on no more; let euery one ſtriue to obtaine a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and then to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue perfect: It is moſt apparant euery one deſires to ſee many dayes, but, it is very doubtfull
<pb facs="tcp:11698:12"/>that few deſires to ſee good dayes; and it is true (for <hi>ipſe dixit</hi>) all thoſe that doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee good dayes, are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to bee partakers of many euill nights; for the decree is out that none can diſanull; thoſe that doe not loue the light, are deomed to bee ſhut vp in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for the vnfortunate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed (vnfortunate to bee vnfurniſhed) wicked man, heard this ſentence denounced againſt him, when in ſpeachleſſe ſilence his eares were forced to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the iudgement of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that in the dayes of peace would not receiue the glad-ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Saluation, Matth. 22. <hi>Binde him hand and foote, and take him away, and caſt him into vtter daskeneſſe, there ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> ſorced howling, and continuall
<pb facs="tcp:11698:12"/>torments, the horrible clamours of the damned ſoules; there is nothing to bee ſeene but darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nothing to bee heard but horror, nothing to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood but confuſion, nothing to be knowne but dolours, nothing to be felt but torments, and laſt of all, which is worſt of all, there is no ende of theſe, they are eternall.</p>
                  <p>And theſe remaines for thoſe that will not put off the workes of darkeneſſe, and put on the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of light, that wil not ceaſe to doe euill, and learne to doe well, that will not caſt away the ragges of wickedneſſe pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with their owne miſeries, and ſeeke the white robes of righteouſneſſe prepared by our Sauiours mercies. There is none (no not the meaneſt) ſhut from the benefit of ſaluation;
<pb facs="tcp:11698:13"/>God hath beſtowed vpon vs the word Incarnate, wherein God was made man, Ioh. 1. <hi>The Word was made fleſh, and dwell amongst vs, and wee ſaw the glory of it as the glory of the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne of God, full of grace and trueth:</hi> ſo that no greater dignity could bee beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, then to be perſonally and bodily ioyned vnto the nature of God in the onely begotten Sonne of God: In few words, man could haue been ſet no nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the God-head, vnles he had been altogether changed into it. Wee are the children of a gracious Father, which hath prouided for euery towardly child an euerlaſting inheritance; therefore ſince the booke is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſealed, let vs bee carefull to ſearch that ſacred Euidence, wherein wee may finde directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:11698:13"/>to land vs in that fayre Countrey, which euery bleſſed ſoule doth ſeeke; and now that it may bee knowne you are bound for Ieruſalem, you muſt forſake thoſe wayes that leads to Babylon, you muſt content your ſelues firſt to endure the croſſe; and the promiſe is, you ſhall after enioy the crowne: and to mooue you to remooue your affections to the world to come, and to refuſe the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the world preſent; If you contemne the voyce of meaner men, heare a King ſpeake, and He is <hi>Rex magnus,</hi> a great King; <hi>Regnans ſuper om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Regna terrae,</hi> Reigning ouer all the Kingdoms of the world, hee aduiſeth vs, Matth. 6.33. <hi>Seeke firſt the Kingdome of heauen and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and all things neceſſary ſhall bee giuen vnto you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:14"/>
                  <p>Now you that are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the world, and the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of it, ſpare a little time to examine what benefites it can afford, that may moue you to put your confidence in it, or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle your loue vpon it, and for your owne ſpeedy ſatisfaction that you may be reſolued in as little time as may bee conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. You that aime to winne the world, conſider but theſe two things: firſt, the quantitie of the purchaſe; ſecondly, the qualitie of the price: and firſt for the firſt.</p>
                  <p>The quality of the purchaſe is great, there is honour praiſe, clothing, worldly wiſedome, riches, and carnall pleaſures, and more, and yet the beſt of theſe are to thoſe that truſt in them worſe then nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, had they beene nothing,
<pb facs="tcp:11698:14"/>they had not been tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed in, therefore they are ſomething nothing worth; for the time wil come (I am afraid) that as Chriſt once ſaid of <hi>Iudas</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, in Matth. 26. <hi>It had been good for that man if hee had not been borne;</hi> ſo a number will ſay of themſelues plurally, It had been good for vs if we had neuer been; for better to haue no being, then to want a being well.</p>
                  <p>But let vs be further ſatisfied. Shall wee account our ſelues happy to enioy earthly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? not as it is earthly; for firſt, it is gotten with much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, kept with great coſts, and loſt with great griefe. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the great men in Iury ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe to deliuer Chriſt to death, then to rob Caeſar, or themſelues, of their dignitie and
<pb facs="tcp:11698:15"/>honour, Ioh. 11. <hi>If wee let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, he doth ſo many miracles, hee will take away both our place and nation, our honour and authority.</hi> O! I feare policie preuailes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt piety, there are too many (two is many, but there is too too many) that prefers tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall honour before eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. It is ſayd, and it is a true report, that <hi>Homo vanitati ſimilis factus est,</hi> Man is made like vnto vanity, for hee looſeth his breath with purſuing ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, or it had not been ſaid, <hi>In vanitate ſua appenditur pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> The ſinner is weighed in his owne vanitie.</p>
                  <p>Where is now the dignities of all our antique Worthies? <hi>Caeſars,</hi> was murthered in the Senate; <hi>Alexanders,</hi> died of poyſon; <hi>Salomons,</hi> is in a dead ſleepe on an adulterous bed;
<pb facs="tcp:11698:15"/>
                     <hi>Abſaloms</hi> was hanged in the cords of diſobedience, <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> tumbled with Babylon, <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> is turned to graſſe, <hi>Siſeraes</hi> is nayled to the ground, <hi>Holofernes</hi> honour is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed by a ſilly woman, <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheribs</hi> is ſlaine in the Temple, <hi>Herods</hi> is conſumed with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, this earthly honour is ſo attended with death and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, that hee that deſires it ſhall in the ende bee found guilty of his owne endleſſe ouerthrow. Honour flies from thoſe that followes it, and followes thoſe that flies it. Who deſired it more then the Monarchs? and who had leſſe? who eſteemed it leſſe then the Apoſtles? and who had more? thoſe that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in honour died with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to liue in endleſſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and thoſe that liued in
<pb facs="tcp:11698:16"/>diſgrace, died with honour to liue in endleſſe glory. Then we muſt not bee thus ſatisfied, but ſeeke ſome better benefice,<note place="margin">Matth. 21.9.</note> for it will profit vs nothing to win worldly honour.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Shal we account our ſelues happie to enioy the praiſe of men?<note place="margin">Luk. 23.21.</note> no; who deſires the fruits of ſtinking breath that is rotten before it bee fully ripe? The heathen ſaith; <hi>Non refert quam multi laudent te, &amp;c.</hi> It forceth not how many praiſe thee, but how good, for to bee praiſed of the wicked is to bee diſpraiſed, it is <hi>Pauls</hi> reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1. Cor. 4. <hi>I paſſe very little to be iudged of men.</hi> There are a number like the Babylonians ſpoken of in the third of <hi>Daniel,</hi> a little ſweete muſicke made them to fall downe and honour <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> new God,
<pb facs="tcp:11698:16"/>and a little flattering &amp; praiſe of men will make a number to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour <hi>Iaacobs</hi> true God. The bright Angels in heauen ſeekes not their owne but their makers worſhip, Reu. 22. <hi>The glorious Elders takes off their Crownes and caſts them at the feet of the Lamb, and ſing not their owne, but their Princes praiſe:</hi> yet man being but a poore worme, would bee extolled, and makes Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants and flatterers the beſt welcome. I can heare none crie with good King <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſa. 141. <hi>Away with this oyle and oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinners, it ſhal not come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my head.</hi> A man may haue the praiſe of a multitude, &amp; yet be neere his fall. Note the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite that came to the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet by mens praiſe, Matth. 22. at Ieſus comming to Iernſalem, the gates were opened, bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires
<pb facs="tcp:11698:17"/>kindled, branches cut, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſpread, trumpets ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the ſacrifice of euery one was, <hi>Hoſanna to the ſonne of Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 21.9.</note> 
                     <hi>bleſſed is he that commeth in the Name of the Lord.</hi> This praiſe was great, but it both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and ended together, they forgot <hi>Hoſanna</hi> in a few houres, and the very ſame lips cried <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifige eum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 23.21.</note> crucifie him, crucifie him. Who couets the praiſe of the people that commends <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabbas</hi> the murderer, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes Ieſus the Sauiour? Let vs maintaine the Apoſtles mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Nolite eſſe pueri ſenſibus,</hi> bee not you children in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: run not after bables, but ſeeke the true treaſures; we are ſet at libertie to gather gold in Canaan, ſhall not wee then diſdain to toyle for ſtraw in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt; let vs ſtretch our beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours
<pb facs="tcp:11698:17"/>to finde ſome better benefice, for it will auaile vs nothing to win worldy praiſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Is any true felicitie to bee found in rich apparell? No, I haue read the King of Cypreſſe hauing put on princely and ſumptuous attire, and being ſet on his Royall throne, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>Solon</hi> if hee euer ſaw a more glorious obiect. <hi>Solon</hi> told him, hee had ſeene cockes, pheaſants, and peacockes, and that hee thought thoſe birds were more beautifull, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their colours were both faire and naturall. It is moſt true, that we are moſt wretched of all creatures, and <hi>miſeros fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit populos peccatum,</hi> ſinne is the thing that makes men miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and wee plucke from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing ſomething to be coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings to our miſeries; one lends
<pb facs="tcp:11698:18"/>vs skinne, another wooll, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other furre, another feathers, another pearle, another gold, another ſilke, another precious ſtones and iewels, yea, euery creature, and euery element af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords ſome things to furniſh vs, and yet wee are as proud of this as if it were ours by nature, when indeede ours is the leaſt part, for if euery creature ſhould come and challenge his owne, all our coſtly couerings would diſſolue to nakedneſſe. Therefore that of <hi>Dauid</hi> cannot bee told too often, Pſalm. 39. <hi>Doubileſſe man walketh in a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and diſquieteth himſelfe in vaine.</hi> Howſoeuer wee drawe curtaines and couerings about vs, to make vs appeare more ſeemely then wee are; yet our ilneſſe will be manifeſt. Clouds that are ouercharged with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:11698:18"/>muſt needes droppe. God is omniuident, and the power of policie cannot preuaile ſo much as to conceale any thing from the Prince of piety: It is not Art, but grace, muſt helpe the defects of nature, we main taine our clothing againſt the Rule of God. Our nobleſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wore coates of skinnes, Gen. 3. The Saints recorded in the booke of God, Hebr. 11. were but clothed in camels haire and goats skinnes. Chriſt ſaid in Luk. 7. they that weare delicate and ſoft apparell, are in Kings houſes (vnderſtand this, leſt you take it for a preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) not fighting in the great Kings campe, but flattering in pettie Princes Courts: to checke vs for our careleſſe wantonneſſe, (in this kinde) there is an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Luke 16. <hi>The rich Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton
<pb facs="tcp:11698:19"/>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> clothed in fine linnen, and curious ſilkes very ſumptuouſly, and fared very deliciouſly,</hi> died very damnably, and ſhall liue in torments eternally. Now you that would auoid his portion, damnation, you muſt deteſt his proportion, ambition; for the command is, <hi>in veſtitu ne glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris vnquam,</hi> ſee thou now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer take glory in thine habite.</p>
                  <p>To preuent the deſtruction which was threatned to <hi>Niniueh</hi> we find in <hi>Ionah</hi> 3. the king com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to keepe a ſolemn feaſt &amp; to frame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as the outward ſigne of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward repentance, &amp; he himſelfe forſooke his Throne, put on ſackecloth, and ſate in aſhes. but was it wiſely done to put on ſo poore attire, to ſtand in before the greateſt king, being to begge his owne and Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uehs
<pb facs="tcp:11698:19"/>pardon? Yes ſurely hee did wonderous well, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that although hee was a king, ſince his power was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht, and that he could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger continue, except hee could begge his libertie at God, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ambition and ſawcineſſe becomes not beggars) hee laid aſide his rich clothing, and poorely went and purchaſed his owne and Niniuehs pardon. O remember <hi>Lazarus</hi> was found in ragges when hee was taken and preferred into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> boſome. And we find, Lu. 2. CHRIST was but poorely lapt in clouts when hee came to conquer ſinne, death, and hell, and yet left the earth with glory and victory. Be aduiſed then, it is not gariſh apparell that will preferre you; obſerue the holy direction, Eccleſ. 9. at all times
<pb facs="tcp:11698:20"/>let thy garments bee white. Clothe your ſelues with inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cencie, and contemne this am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious furniture; all the gaine comes by it is this, It makes Chriſtians that ſhould die like lambes, to die like dogges, their skinnes prooue better then their bodies O keepe your ſelues free from this pride and vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, that you may (without bluſhing) diſdaine ſuch compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, and ſhewe your ſelues guiltleſſe, and then ſeeke ſome other preferment, for it wil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit vs nothing to practiſe proud attire.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Next, for worldly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it is little worth, there comes no laſting aduancement by it, becauſe 4. Cor. 3. <hi>The wiſedome of the world is folly with God.</hi> The wiſe men of the world Chriſt did ſeldome or neuer
<pb facs="tcp:11698:20"/>chuſe to doe him any ſeruice, for, <hi>non multi ſapientes ſecundum carnem.</hi> When the Meſsias was promiſed to come to bee the king of the Iewes, they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a great earthly Prince, a Royall Caeſar, and refuſed Chriſt, becauſe hee came in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, ſo hee was vnto them a ſtumbling blocke, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſauouring of nought but earthly wiſedome, thought it was a thing vnlike, and meere folly for the Sonne of God, to leaue his Throne in heauen (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo glorious) to deſcend to earth to taſte of mans miſeries, ſo hee was to them fooliſhneſſe, 1. Cor. 1. <hi>This is worldly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and who can be happy in it?</hi> this ſhall one day be the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-wiſe mans confeſsion, <hi>Nos inſenſati vitam i'lorum aeſ imaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus inſaniam,</hi> Wiſ. 5. Wee foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb facs="tcp:11698:21"/>men eſteemed the liues of Saints to be but madneſſe: this ſhall be many of our wiſe mens confeſsion, when their confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comes too late to haue a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; the wiſedom of the world is no more profitable, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none can be happie in it. In times paſt the Apoſtles prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched Chriſt crucified (with the manner of his offering, and the merite of his ſuffering) and the Philoſophers and wiſe men of the world accounted them fooles for their paines.</p>
                  <p>Indeed the time preſent doth not much alter from the time paſt, when the miniſters of God tooke, or takes paines for the fooles, they ſhall be accounted fooles for their paines, for that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itle is the beſt that the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the world allowes them, but the Saints of God
<pb facs="tcp:11698:21"/>haue all his meſſengers in great regard, for the good turnes done by the maſter, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth well the iuſt to bee thankefull: therefore be better aduiſed and ſeeke better trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſince there is no true profit in worldly wiſedome.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 For riches, I ſay to you as <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> ſaid to his man that carried his treaſure after him. That which is too waighty caſt out. and that which thou canſt well, carrie. So caſt away ſuch triflles as are needleſſe, &amp; keepe ſuch treaſures as you may with eaſe and without danger vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, as neceſſary. Theſe riches are but thornes, they are but miſeries and afflictions. And we ſee, <hi>quomodo ſuffocant,</hi> how they do choake vs, by ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them too greedy. <hi>Paul</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed all riches but as dung.
<pb facs="tcp:11698:22"/>Phil. 3. <hi>They are indeed but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelfe.</hi> We find that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon</hi> was the moſt abſolute pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of worldly proſperitie. 1. Kings 4. <hi>Gold and ſiluer was as plentifull with him as ſtones,</hi> So much, that the abundance of both, made both little eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; his iewels and plate were not to be valued, his pretious apparell and armour was infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, his Throne of Maieſtie was borne vp with twelue Lyons of gold, farre exceeding all other kingly ſeats in the world: all the veſſels of his houſe were of pure gold, for ſiluer was not eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the dayes of <hi>Solomon:</hi> He had all the Kings from the riuer of the Philiſtians to Egypt to ſerue him. Hee had fortie thouſand horſes in his ſtables to ride. He had 12. thouſand Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots and horſes, with furniture
<pb facs="tcp:11698:22"/>to them for his vſe. Hee had two hundred ſpeares, and three hundred ſhieldes of beaten gold borne before him, and it is ſaid that he ſpent in bread euery day in his houſe one thouſand nine hundred thirtie and ſeuen quarters of meale and floure, he ſpent in fleſh thirtie fat oxen, an hundred ſheepe, beſides Harts, Buckes, and fat Foule; He had ſeuen hundred Queenes, and three hundred Concubines; were not theſe things verified in the ſacred Hiſtorie, I ſhould bluſh to report them; becauſe they almoſt ſeeme impoſsible: and therfore incredible, yet not theſe, but more things the holy Scripture teſtifies of <hi>Salomons</hi> worldly riches and proſperitie: but now ſince he inioyed all theſe things in his dayes, let vs know how he was ſatisfied in
<pb facs="tcp:11698:23"/>the euening, and whether he went content and pleaſed to his bed or no? no that he did not: for hauing fully and largely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all the beſt content that thoſe riches could afford; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuers theſe words from his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied mind, with a diſliking voyce. Fccleſ. 1 <hi>Vanitas vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum, &amp; omnia vanitas,</hi> Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of vanities, and all is vanitie; thoſe that now will not, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall repent when this remedileſſe complaint, (ſhall come too late.) <hi>Diuitiarum Iactantia quid nobis contulit.</hi> What hath the brauery of our riches profited vs? none at all. They can doe the poſſeſſors of them no good, when they haue moſt neede of helpe, Prou. 11. <hi>They cannot profit a man in the day of wrath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I haue read that <hi>Byas Priennaeus</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:23"/>a Sage of Greece, beholding his Countrey ouerthrowne by his enemies, forſook it, &amp; fled with his neighbours, &amp; they carried away ſo much of their riches, as by all means they could, &amp; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him goe ſo ſingly and beare nothing but himſelf, demanded of him why he left his treaſure behind him; he anſwered, my treaſure is in my breſt, I take it, yours is but vpon you backes: you miſtake it; it is in the power of the enemie to make you poore; and no change, no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap, no enemy can take my treaſure, for whilſt I haue a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am rich, and when I am not, I am not poore: his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion deſerues eternall memory; it is look't for in a Chriſtian, but it is ſtrange to heare a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then eſteeme all things vanity: Man is like vnto a rouling
<pb facs="tcp:11698:24"/>wheele that runs about from day to day, and yet it is but in the ſame place at the yeers end, where it was in the beginning. So man toyles and labours all his time vpon earth to gather wealth and riches, and yet is as poore vpon that day he dies, as he was vpon that day he was borne. Therefore I ſay to you as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1. Tim. 6. <hi>We brought nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, and it is certaine we can carry nothing out.</hi> Therfore, if we haue food and raiment let vs therewith be content: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſits reioycing and ſinging in a ſuppoſed chaire of ſtate (&amp; indeed 'its rather a truth then a ſuppoſition; for it is a chaire of contented eſtate,) and ſmiles to ſee the couetous worldling take ſuch paines to make other men pleaſure; and although the
<pb facs="tcp:11698:24"/>contented man be but tenant to a poore Cottage, coucred but with ſtraw or clods of earth, ſheltered from the violence of the winds, with the curled tops of the ſhadie trees: ſuch a one as he may ſtand in the middle and touch the roofe with his head, and both wals with both his hands. Yet he heares not of the mutation in the Court, he feares not their diſimulation in the Citie; but liues richly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent in a poore home: you ſee the Cottage is as much worth as the Court, but for the ſhow. Weake walles of clay, giues as much aſſurance of ſafety, as walles of ſtone lined with Wainſcot or cloth of Arras; all the oddes is in the ſhow. The poore man ſleepes as ſoundly vpon his bed of ſtraw, as the rich man vpon his bed of
<pb facs="tcp:11698:25"/>downe; and the difference is but in the ſhow: and the mean man is kept as warme in countrey ruſſet and homely gray, as the mightieſt man in his cloth of gold, and curious ſilkes; yet all the oddes is in the ſhow: the poore mans woollen cap, keepes his head as drie, as the rich mans beauer; they only but dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in the ſhow: a browne cruſt, and fountaine water, preſerues the poore man in health, as well as the rich man is kept with his dainteſt cates, &amp; pureſt wine; ſtil the difference is in the ſhow: a wooden diſh is as wholeſome to drinke in, as a cup of gold; but for the ſhow: the rich man exceeds the poore for the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, the colour and the ſhow; but the poore man exceeds the rich for the quality, the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſubſtance: the rich
<pb facs="tcp:11698:25"/>mans part is greater, but the poore mans part is better: and I know not how it happens, they were both ſet to run one courſe, and the rich hath all the honour and glory of it from the poore in the middle of it; but ſure I am, they were both alike in the beginning, and ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in the end. <hi>Aut in vtero, aut in vrna, Senec. Epiſt.</hi> 91. Either in the wombe, or in the tombe. <hi>Interuallis distinguimur, exitu e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quamur,</hi> It is the interim of this ſhort life, that we are ſomewhat in ſome things vnlike: ſome are Lords of more, and of leſſe; ſome are Princes, and ſome are beggars, and ſome winne the world, and ſome loſe it; and ſome haue much, and are not pleaſed, and ſome haue little, &amp; are well content: but Ex. 16. <hi>He that gathers much hath nothing
<pb facs="tcp:11698:26"/>ouer, and he that gathers little, hath not the leſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qui dilligit auram non iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabitur,</hi> Hee that loueth gold, ſhall neuer be iuſtified, and the words of Chriſt are, Matth. 19. <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, a rich man can hardly enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God:</hi> becauſe ſome take ſo much care and toyle to lay vp treaſure together vpon earth, which theeues, and moths, and canker conſume, and are both negligent, and vnwilling, to lay vp treaſure in heauen; ſuch ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their minds onely vpon earth, with earthly riches ſhall periſh: and prouiding no trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure heauenly, in heauen ſhall neuer come. Iames 5. <hi>Go to now you rich men, weepe and howle for the miſerie that ſhall come vpon you:</hi> your riches are corrupt, your garmentsare moth-eaten,
<pb facs="tcp:11698:26"/>your gold and ſiluer are can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kred, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe againſt you, and ſhall eat your fleſh vp, as it were fire: you haue heaped vp wrath for the laſt dayes. A man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts his riches his beſt friend to accompany, relieue, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort a man in aduerſitie: and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches can neuer doe it. They are like flatterers, which when a man is in moſt need, will do him leaſt good; for they ſhall not profit him in the day of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: neuertheleſſe, the rich man is confident in the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I conceiue ſo much in his carriage, for hee hath erected faire and ſumptuous building, deckt his habitation with richeſt furniture, furniſht his lodgings with beds of down, fil'd his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions with ſtore of cattle, ſtuff'd his barnes with pureſt
<pb facs="tcp:11698:27"/>corne; prouided for his diet the daintieſt meat choſen, for his backe the richeſt clothing, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for his eares the ſweeteſt muſicke, flatters himſelfe with with a ſuppoſed content, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes himſelfe into the roome of his plenty, ſcats himſelfe in the chaire of ingratitude, and ſhuts vpon him the doore of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, numbers the angels in his cheſts; and forgets the Articles of his Creed, throwes himſelfe vpon his bed of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and there fals into a golden dreame, and wakening, vtters this reſolute ſpeech, Luke 12. <hi>Soule, thou hast much goods laid vp for many yeeres, liue at eaſe, eate, ſleepe, and take thy pleaſure.</hi> But this would not laſt, his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute reſolution had a reſolute diſolution. Foole this night they will take away thy ſoule,
<pb facs="tcp:11698:27"/>and whoſe ſhall all theſe things be which thou haſt prouided. Thus it happens to thoſe that truſt in their riches. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet demaunds, <hi>Baruch</hi> 3. <hi>Where are they now which hoarded vp ſiluer &amp; gold, wherin they truſted, and made no end of ſcraping toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Hee anſweres himſelfe: <hi>Exterminati ſunt &amp; ad Inferos deſcenderunt,</hi> They are now roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out and gone downe into hell. Therefore, woe be vnto the rich, for they haue receiued their conſolation, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. Like vnto vnthrifty heires, ſold all, and ſpent all; to whom, and for whom, nothing remaines but miſery. Then ſince the wealth of the world is worthleſſe, and yeelds no perfit happineſſe, but for a time flatters fooles, and leaues them vnſatisfied. It ſhall be our care to finde out ſome
<pb facs="tcp:11698:28"/>better benefit, for it will profit vs nothing to winne worldly riches.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Shall wee account our ſelues happie to practiſe carnall pleaſure? no, no; yet God hath allowed a certaine meaſure of carnall recreations for the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for the maintenance of their healths: theſe I doe not intend to prooue, but to reproue that exceſſe &amp; abundance, in which worldly men vſe them: banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſpeaking, laughing, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. Theſe are the chiefe parts of carnall pleaſures. There is danger in banquetings: <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great feaſting in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, after he had conquered the whole world, ſitting there to reioyce, and caſt lots, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the kingdoms, the end of his banquet, was the end of his life; amongſt all his dainties, he died
<pb facs="tcp:11698:28"/>of poyſon. <hi>Holofernes,</hi> after his banquet, being full of wine, fell into a heauy ſleepe, and paid his head for his pleaſures, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith</hi> 13. and ſo he found a heauy reckoning. Yet this exceſſe in banqueting takes not away the bleſſing of feaſting: neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, make the banquet without exceſſe, and ſee it vſed in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate kind, and it is a good, but the diſcontinuance of it, makes it imperfect: hunger ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enſues the beſt feeding, ſo that our beſt title I can giue this carnall pleaſure, is a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome cuſtome that yeelds more profit then delight.</p>
                  <p>There is danger in ſpeaking, ſince, Matth. 12. <hi>For euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue an account thereof at the day of iudgement;</hi> There is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in laughing, for Eccleſ. 2. <hi>I
<pb facs="tcp:11698:29"/>haue ſaid of laughter, thou art mad, and of ioy, what is this that thou doeſt.</hi> There is danger in playing and wantonneſſe, and ſo <hi>Sampſon</hi> loſt his ſtrength, <hi>Iudges</hi> 16. So did <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtaine his honour, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. There is danger in ſleeping, Two ſhalbe lying in one bed, the one ſhalbe taken, the other refuſed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. Danger lies lurking vnder the faireſt roofe, the moſt ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous buildings are but ſhadowes, for the time ſhall come, that one ſtone ſhall not be left vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Marke</hi> 13. Therefore, hee that hath eares to heare may heare, he that hath eyes to ſee, may ſee, he that hath ſence to leare, may learne, the world is worthleſſe, the purchace need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the plenties of it helpleſſe, the louers of it hapleſſe, the pleaſures in it fruitleſſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:11698:29"/>the torments after it endleſſe. Nothing to bee found in the world but troubles, miſeries, night, need, and plenty of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content; and no better treaſure then is herein diſcouered vnto you, is to be found in the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the purchace.</p>
                  <p>Nowe the qualitie of the price is the ſoule, and what ſhall it profit a man to win the whole world, and to looſe his owne ſoule? The ſoule is an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall ſubſtance, and the proper ſeat of the image of God, and 't is the nobleſt part of man: as the poore cottage of clay may lodge the mightieſt Prince, ſo our poore clods of ſoyle were but made to lodge the ſoule, the body being the baſer, is made a chamber for the ſoule, which is the better; and vpon the ſoule God hath beſtowed eternity, it
<pb facs="tcp:11698:30"/>had a beginning, but hath no ending; which ſhall either vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the forſaking of his earthly manſion, find perpetuall ioy, or laſting torments; and who to win the world, which is but a winters day, feares not to ſend the ſoule to endleſſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into euerlaſting night? If there be any faith, there is ſome feare, but I feare, <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>grotat fides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am proxima morti.</hi> Faith is ſo ſicke that it is ready to die; and if it be ſo, we haue loſt our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chour and are but in a broken Barke vpon the great ſeas of miſerie, all things to nothing ſodainly to periſh.</p>
                  <p>But to come to an end (and I beſeech God my now ending may be a numbers good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.) Since the quality of the price, the immortall ſoule farre exceedes the quantitie of the
<pb facs="tcp:11698:30"/>purchace, the worthles world, my aduiſe is to forſake theſe Netherlands, and lift your eyes vnto the heauens, for from thence muſt come your helpe. <hi>Coloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> If you be then riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe things that are aboue. And as the ſpies did that fled from Iericho, ſo ſaue your ſelues and eſcape by hils. It is the diuels councell, <hi>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te deorſum,</hi> throwe thy ſelfe downe, ſet thy affections vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earthly things, delight in the world: but doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it, aime at better ends, nay aime at that which hath no ende, and as you ſee God hath ordained the end, ſo hee hath done the meanes, then vſe the world as the means to obtaine heauen, vnto the hauen, the heauen of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and glory he that is Lord
<pb facs="tcp:11698:31"/>of all, bring vs all for his mercies and merits ſake: to him be all praiſe and glory now and for euer. Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:31"/>
                  <p>THE COMMING OF THE KINGS SONNE.</p>
                  <q>Behold, I come ſhortly, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is with me. <bibl>
                        <hi>Reuel. 22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Quiſquis ad vitam editur, ad mortem deſtinatur.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>Compoſed By AVGVSTIN TAYLOR, <hi>Preacher at</hi> Hawarden.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Augustine Matthewes,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Parſonage houſe in Bride Lane, neere Fleet-ſtreet. 1623.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:32"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ARTHVR Lord Chicheſter, Baron of Belfaſt, &amp;c.</head>
                  <l>IT cannot be but as you haue</l>
                  <l>Worne death vpon your ſword</l>
                  <l>And purchac'd honour, you ſhould ſaue</l>
                  <l>One Swan vpon your ford</l>
                  <l>To ſing you meaſures, you before</l>
                  <l>Haue march'd like <hi>Dauid</hi> King</l>
                  <l>And ſince like him you conqueſt wore</l>
                  <l>Now ſet you downe and ſing:</l>
                  <l>Or hearken me, my Lord I'm free</l>
                  <l>To ſing, and my ſong's true;</l>
                  <l>Ornated with Diuinitie,</l>
                  <l>And doth belong to you,</l>
                  <l>Your noble nature, valour, and</l>
                  <l>Moſt Lordly bounty, ſhould</l>
                  <l>Be writ by an Euangels hand,</l>
                  <l>In lines of perfect gold.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:33"/>
                  <l>Mine are diuine (although vnmeet)</l>
                  <l>Accept them, I haue power</l>
                  <l>To build another Lanthorne yet</l>
                  <l>Vpon your ſtateli'ſt tower.</l>
                  <l>Thrice noble Lord make vſe of this,</l>
                  <l>'Twill tell you of a ſonne</l>
                  <l>That ſhall ſhine in the dayes of blis,</l>
                  <l>When nights of woes are done.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>At your Honours ſeruice, in any Chriſtian office.</hi> Auguſtin Taylor.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:33"/>
                  <head>THE COMMING OF THE KINGS SONNE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="1">1 O Iſrael that thou would heare</l>
                     <l>And vnderſtand thoſe things</l>
                     <l>That God commands, for loue or feare</l>
                     <l>Of the great King of Kings</l>
                     <l>Reforme thy ſelfe, the dayes doth run</l>
                     <l>And poſteth faſt away</l>
                     <l>The time departs, and th'euening ſun</l>
                     <l>Is finiſhing the day.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="2">2 The beames of mercy will grow dim,</l>
                     <l>Offences grow ſo great,</l>
                     <l>The times are now ſo ſicke with ſinne</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> dare ſcarce intreat</l>
                     <l>Thy pardon any more of God,</l>
                     <l>Thy promiſe was to mend,</l>
                     <l>And he in mercy ſtayes the rod,</l>
                     <l>And doth thy time attend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:34"/>
                     <l n="3">3 The dayes of peace are almoſt paſt,</l>
                     <l>And nights of death enſue</l>
                     <l>Vengeance black cloud will drop at laſt</l>
                     <l>The newes are bad, yet true;</l>
                     <l>The goulden bels at <hi>Aarons</hi> coat</l>
                     <l>Haue almoſt loſt their ſound,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dauids</hi> ſweet Harpe, and Cymbals note,</l>
                     <l>The thundring trump hath dround.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="4">4 Behold the Sonne of God doth come</l>
                     <l>Not Lambe, but Lyon-like</l>
                     <l>With life to all the righteous ſome</l>
                     <l>And with blacke death to ſtrike</l>
                     <l>The curſed brood of prophane <hi>Cham,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A diſmall time comes on</l>
                     <l>When God will grant the wicked man</l>
                     <l>No place to reſt vpon.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="5">5 The bondleſſe ſea with fire ſhall burne.</l>
                     <l>The Hils ſhall leape and daunce</l>
                     <l>But not for ioy; all fleſh ſhall mourne</l>
                     <l>And who preſumes t' aduance</l>
                     <l>His eyes to heauen there ſhall view,</l>
                     <l>The ſtarres goe out and fall,</l>
                     <l>The Skies ſhall change their Azur blew</l>
                     <l>To Crimſonred, and all</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:34"/>
                     <l n="6">6 The furniture of ayre and earth</l>
                     <l>Shall periſh and decay,</l>
                     <l>Mourning ſhall come in ſteed of mirth,</l>
                     <l>And night inſteed of day:</l>
                     <l>The now bright ſunne ſhall then appeare</l>
                     <l>A cloud fild full of raine,</l>
                     <l>The moone that ſometime lookt ſo cleare</l>
                     <l>Before the ſtarrie traine</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="7">7 Shall looke like blood, and looſe her pace,</l>
                     <l>Sad witneſſes of ire,</l>
                     <l>Shall multiply in fearefull caſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſtormes and ſhowers, of fire</l>
                     <l>Thicker then hayle did ere deſcend</l>
                     <l>Shall fall as (as Prophets cry)</l>
                     <l>Since for mans ſinne, God did intend,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid, all fleſh ſhall die.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="8">8 After theſe ſtormes and fearefull ſignes,</l>
                     <l>The Kings ſonne in a cloud</l>
                     <l>Shall ſit as Iudge: to whom inclines</l>
                     <l>The eares of all the crowd</l>
                     <l>There ſhall be all that borrowed breath,</l>
                     <l>As well the great as ſmall,</l>
                     <l>From the worlds birth day to it death</l>
                     <l>And lateſt funerall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:35"/>
                     <l n="9">9 The Princes, Kings, and Monarchs great</l>
                     <l>That once the world did ſway,</l>
                     <l>Shall naked ſtand before the ſeat</l>
                     <l>Of the high Iudge, that day.</l>
                     <l>The nice and tender wanton crew</l>
                     <l>That now doe ſcorne the ground,</l>
                     <l>And doe diſdaine the ſun ſhould view,</l>
                     <l>Their faces ſhall be found</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="10">10 Bare face and foot, without a coach</l>
                     <l>No man, no maid, no knees</l>
                     <l>T'adore their greatneſſe, but reproch</l>
                     <l>For their proud qualities.</l>
                     <l>There <hi>Lazarus</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> meet,</l>
                     <l>And the ſpectators can</l>
                     <l>Not cenſure (by their equall greet)</l>
                     <l>Which is the greater man.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="11">11 The ſupreame Iudge aboue ſhall ſit</l>
                     <l>In glory ſtrength and might,</l>
                     <l>The godly ſhall reioyce at it,</l>
                     <l>The righteous ſhall haue right;</l>
                     <l>No bribes, nor friends, nor flatters may</l>
                     <l>Preuaile, to hide offence,</l>
                     <l>For why? God onely made that day</l>
                     <l>To honour innocence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:35"/>
                     <l n="12">12 God is ſo gratious, the condemn'd</l>
                     <l>Can haue no cauſe to grudge,</l>
                     <l>Which doth all dayes in mercy ſpend</l>
                     <l>And keepes but one to iudge.</l>
                     <l>But great and fearefull will it be</l>
                     <l>The thoughts of euery heart,</l>
                     <l>Shall be reueil'd apparantly,</l>
                     <l>And after each deſert.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="13">13 Rewards ſhall run; it's Gods decree</l>
                     <l>All wickedneſſe ſhall faile</l>
                     <l>And fall, and periſh vtterly,</l>
                     <l>And puritie preuaile:</l>
                     <l>Againſt this iudgement who prouides,</l>
                     <l>Or who with <hi>Iob</hi> demands</l>
                     <l>What ſhall I doe? life runs and ſlides</l>
                     <l>Like vnto dyall ſands.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="14">14 Falls to be lift againe; might I</l>
                     <l>Friendly perſwaſion vſe</l>
                     <l>And ſee it follow'd, none ſhould ſpie</l>
                     <l>Sad paſsion in my muſe.</l>
                     <l>Hate enuy, murther, blaſphemie,</l>
                     <l>Detraction, and all vice,</l>
                     <l>Contract your ſelues to puritie</l>
                     <l>Or to his Paradice.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11698:36"/>
                     <l n="15">15 This iudge admits you not; beware</l>
                     <l>That run not out of mind,</l>
                     <l>That he intends for to declare</l>
                     <l>He ſhowd himſelfe ſo kind</l>
                     <l>To publiſh it in dayes of peace</l>
                     <l>Where by we know's intent</l>
                     <l>Intends, if ſinne ſpring and increaſe,</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo ſhall puniſhment.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="16">16 You bleſſed, come; you curſed goe;</l>
                     <l>So hath the iudge decreed,</l>
                     <l>And that his bleſsings you may know,</l>
                     <l>Furniſh your ſelues with ſpeed,</l>
                     <l>For the right hand, and let our foes</l>
                     <l>Siniſter paſſage trie</l>
                     <l>That leads to torments, death and woes,</l>
                     <l>God grant both you and I</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="17">17 May tread the path that leads to peace,</l>
                     <l>And when our dayes of grace</l>
                     <l>Are finiſhed let neuer ceaſe</l>
                     <l>Our dayes of Glory. Place</l>
                     <l>Vs all aboue, with all our friends;</l>
                     <l>And from all woes beneath,</l>
                     <l>Aſsigne vs bleſſe that neuer ends</l>
                     <l>Both free from dumbe and death.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11698:36"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
